<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Post nubila Phoebus, or, A sermon of thanksgiving for the safe and happy returne of our gracious soveraign ... preached in the city of Aberden at the desire of the lord provest, bailies and councell thereof, upon the XIX [19] day of Iune / by Iohn Patersone ...</title>
            <author>Paterson, John, 1604?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12958573</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12958573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 363:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Post nubila Phoebus, or, A sermon of thanksgiving for the safe and happy returne of our gracious soveraign ... preached in the city of Aberden at the desire of the lord provest, bailies and councell thereof, upon the XIX [19] day of Iune / by Iohn Patersone ...</title>
                  <author>Paterson, John, 1604?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iames Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96048:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſt nubila Phoebus</hi> Or A SERMON OF <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> For the ſafe and happy <hi>Returne</hi> of our gracious SOVERAIGN, to His Ancient DOMINIONS, and Reſtauration to His juſt and Native <hi>DIGNITY, ROYALTIES and GOVERNMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached in the City of <hi>Aberden,</hi> at the deſire of the LORD <hi>PROVEST, Bailies,</hi> and <hi>Councell</hi> thereof, upon the XIX day of <hi>Iune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>IOHN PATERSONE</hi> Miniſter of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> in the ſaid <hi>BVRGH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 20.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Mercy and truth preſerve the King, and his Throne is upholden by mercy.</p>
               <p>Let the KINGS Enemies become a Portion for <hi>Foxes.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDENE,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iames Brown,</hi> Ann. DOM. M.DC.LX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96048:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96048:2"/>
            <head>Unto the <hi>Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, GILBERT GRAY,</hi> LORD PROVOST. And Unto the <hi>Right Honourable, JOHN JAF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FRAY,</hi> Late PROVOST.
<list>
                  <head>Baylies.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WILLIAM GRAY,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ALEX. ROBERTSONE,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ALEX. ALEXANDER,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>ROBERT PETRIE,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>PATRICK MOIR,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>GILBERT MOLY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SONE,</hi> Late <hi>Baylies.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Duncan,</hi> Dean of Gild,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Burnet</hi> Theſaurer: And Remnant Honourable <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours</hi> of the City of <hi>Aberden</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Mercer,</hi> Late Dean of Gild</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Mitchell,</hi> Late Theſaurer:</item>
                  <item>And whole Remnant of the Late honourable <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Aberd.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Day of BRITAIN'S <hi>ſolemnities,</hi> for the Happy <hi>Returne</hi> and <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of our Most Gracious and Illustrious <hi>KING,</hi> ſafe in His Perſon and ſound in the truth of <hi>Religion</hi> (after ſuch a long and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall <hi>Abſence</hi>) to His Ancient <hi>Dominions,</hi> and to His native <hi>Royalties</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> is ſuch an tranſcendent temporall <hi>Mercy,</hi> as deſerves to be writen, not only on <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Marble,</hi> and with a <hi>Diamond</hi> and <hi>Pen</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> but upon the <hi>Spirits</hi> of all, who are truely <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Loyall</hi> within <hi>BRITAINE</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And it cannot be expected, but ſuch an great &amp; merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Revolution,</hi> brought about in ſuch an unanimous, peaceable, ſweet way, without bloud, will be exceedingly magnified and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> by all ſucceeding <hi>Generations,</hi> ſo long as <hi>SCOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND ENGLAND</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> remains to be <hi>NATIONS.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96048:3"/>
And who are ſo ſtupid? but muſt look upon this, at an ſignall token for good, that after ſuch an great <hi>State-quake,</hi> and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning in theſe three <hi>KINGDOMS,</hi> when all concernments in them were wrap'd up in <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> when mens thoughts were quivering, like the needle in the Sea compaſſe and knew not where to rest, The LORD ſhould have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, even then, in ſuch a ſudden, to concenter the hearts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of theſe three <hi>NATIONS,</hi> in the <hi>KINGS MAIESTY,</hi> his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> as the only earthly <hi>Foundation</hi> of their <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> This admirable <hi>Mercy,</hi> hath brought forth many loud and Publique Acclamations of joy in all <hi>Cities, Counties, Incorporations</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of the three <hi>LANDS,</hi> and indeed <hi>Duty</hi> to <hi>GOD ALMIGHTY,</hi> who hath made his own <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me bare</hi> in our <hi>Deliverance, Duty</hi> to Our <hi>SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAIGNE</hi> the <hi>KING,</hi> GOD His immediat <hi>Vice-gerent</hi> over us, the <hi>Duty</hi> which wee owe to Our <hi>Conſciences, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> at home &amp; abroad, cals for very ſingular appearances, and reſentments of ſuch an eminent <hi>Bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt many other His <hi>MAIESTIES</hi> Royall Burghs in <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> I beleeve none (be it ſpoken without envy or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement) did appeare more early, and with greater alacrity and cheerfulneſſe in the publique and ſolemne manifeſtations of their Joy, for His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> ſafe and happy <hi>Returne</hi> and <hi>Reſtauration</hi> to His juſt <hi>Government,</hi> nor this <hi>City</hi> did, which hath alwayes accounted its <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to its native <hi>KING,</hi> its chiefe earthly <hi>Ornament;</hi> whereof it hath many teſtimonies and evidences ſtanding in publique <hi>Regiſter,</hi> and during His <hi>MAIESTY'S</hi> ſad dayes, &amp; abſence, none loved His <hi>MAIESTY</hi> more, none Prayed more heartily, none longed more earneſtly, nor ABERDENE did, for that bleſſed day of His <hi>MAIESTIES Returne</hi> and <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> which the right hand of the LORD hath at last brought to Paſſe: Beſide many other very Solemne and Publique <hi>Manifeſtations</hi> of the <hi>joy</hi> of this <hi>CITY,</hi> for this <hi>Mercy,</hi> never to be forgotten, it was your <hi>HONOURS</hi> command, that the following <hi>Sermon,</hi> being prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="tcp:96048:3"/>
in your <hi>Pulpit</hi> at your deſyre, ſhould be put to the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> &amp; although the Conſcience of my own weakneſſe, and the worthleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of any thing, which can drop from my <hi>Mouth</hi> or <hi>Pen,</hi> might and would have put mee, from any appearance in Print, Yet the ſubject being ſo <hi>Royall,</hi> and at ſuch a nick of time, and my reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects to your <hi>HONOURS</hi> being ſo many and ſo preſſing, have prevailed with mee to let this poor <hi>Mite</hi> of yours and my own <hi>Loyalty,</hi> appeare on the Stage of a Criticke <hi>World, Veritas non querit angulca:</hi> I know I muſt meet with Cenſurers, but if men will cenſure <hi>Truth</hi> harſhly, it will ſtand upon its own joints, and if they cenſure my meane conceptions, and expreſſions, I can ſuffer that eaſily, for it is the matter and not the manner, that I have chiefly aimed at, which makes this paper come out, in its <hi>naked Simplicity,</hi> without <hi>Ornaments.</hi> Whatever it is, I have put it under your <hi>Patrociny,</hi> and I lay it down at your feet as a ſmall testimony of my many <hi>Obligations</hi> and <hi>Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to your <hi>HONOURS</hi> and to this <hi>Honourable City.</hi> The LORD multiply His Spirit and Grace upon you, that you may go on, to act for the Glory of GOD, for the Power of GODLYNES, for the KINGS MAJESTY'S happineſſe, and for the Good and Proſperity of this <hi>People.</hi> So Prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours affection at ſervant in the Work of the Miniſtry, Mr. JO: PATERSONE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb facs="tcp:96048:4"/>
            <head>From a very Reverend and Faithfull BROTHER: <hi>Mr. William Dowglaſſe,</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> in the KINGS CO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEDGE of the Univerſity of <hi>Aberden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY thoughts of this SERMOM, after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall, are as followes.</p>
            <p>That the whole <hi>Draught</hi> is plaine, pertinent and powerfull: That the <hi>Obſerves</hi> have ſuch a naturall and genuine <hi>ariſe,</hi> and the <hi>Uſes</hi> are ſo conſequentially flowing from the <hi>Obſerves</hi> and <hi>Doctrines,</hi> that the committing of it to the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> shall tend much to the publick good; And ſo much the rather, That herein is holden forth what have been the publick <hi>faults</hi> of theſe three NATIONS: as alſo pointing pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually at our <hi>duties,</hi> wee owe moſt to O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R SOVERAIGNE: both which are to very good purpoſe, branched out in many particulars. This is teſtified (though much more might be ſaid) by my ſubſcription.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> W. DOWGLAS.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At Old</hi> Aberdene, <date>
                     <hi>AUGUST 4. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:96048:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF <hi>Thanksgiving:</hi> For the ſafe and happy <hi>Returne</hi> of our SOVERAIGN LORD, <hi>CHARLES</hi> the SECOND, by the Grace of GOD: KING of great <hi>Britaine, France &amp; Ireland,</hi> Defender of the <hi>faith,</hi> to His Ancient DOMINIONS, and Reſtauration to His juſt and Native <hi>DIGNITY, ROY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALTIES and GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. CXXVI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl> When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion: Wee were lyke them that dream.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl> Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee may look upon this day, as upon the ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging up, of a bright &amp; faire morning, after a cloudie dark night, wherin ſo many beaſts of prey did creepe out of their den's, and lurking places of their hatefull and helliſh
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96048:5"/>
               <hi>Hypocriſie:</hi> we may look upon it, as the beginning of a ſweet calme, after a long and dangerous ſtorme; as upon the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an heavy and ſad yoke, which hath lyon ſore upon the necks of theſe three Kingdoms, <hi>SCOTLAND, ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND &amp; IRELAND;</hi> in the wreathing whereof, ſome of this Nation cannot juſtly plead innocency: Wee may look upon this day, as the beginning of a bleſſed <hi>Peace,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a time of much innocent bloud: as upon a day of a civill <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> after a long civill or rather incivill <hi>Death:</hi> as a day long wiſhed and prayed for, by all the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly godly in the three Kingdoms, who have not learned that fanatique and overturning PRINCIPLE, to divorce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which GOD hath ſo nearly and ſtrictly united; And therefore the Lord hath called the Land to <hi>Rejoycing,</hi> and to ſongs of <hi>Praiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Jubilation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note>Theſe words of the <hi>Text,</hi> May be taken up in <hi>five poynts.</hi> I. Wee have the <hi>Condition</hi> of the Jews before the time of their releaſe and delivery came. They were in BONDAGE. <hi>(When the Lord brought back the Captivity of Zion:)</hi> They were under the power and ſlavery of their Conquerours, the <hi>Babylonians.</hi> II. Wee have their <hi>Deliverance,</hi> the looſing of their <hi>Captivity,</hi> with their <hi>Reduction</hi> to their native Countrey. <hi>(Brought back the Captivity of Zion:)</hi> III. Wee have the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of their <hi>Delyverance,</hi> it was not <hi>Themſelves,</hi> not their own <hi>wiſdome,</hi> nor <hi>Power,</hi> nor <hi>Policie,</hi> not the arme of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> but GOD, &amp; GOD alone. <hi>(When the Lord &amp;c.)</hi> IV. How the looſing of them from <hi>Captivity</hi> and their <hi>Reduction</hi> from <hi>Bondage</hi> did affect them, at firſt they wer ſo ſurpriſed with it, that they could not beleeve, that it was a true &amp; reall <hi>Thing,</hi> they looked on it as a <hi>Dream. (We were lyke them that dream.)</hi> V. The <hi>Effects</hi> which the ſenſe of their <hi>Delyverie</hi> did work upon them, after that the <hi>Amazement</hi> was a little allayed, &amp; theſe were, <hi>Rejoycing</hi> and <hi>Mirth. (Then was our mouth filled with laughter &amp; our tongue with ſinging.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The <hi>first Thing</hi> conſiderable in the words, is, the JEWS con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, before the Lord viſited them with this mighty and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96048:5"/>
gracious <hi>Deliverance.</hi> They were in bondage and ſlavery. <hi>(When the LORD brought back the captivity of ZION:)</hi> by <hi>ZION,</hi> wee ar to underſtand the two <hi>Tribes,</hi> or the KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM of <hi>Judah,</hi> comprehending both their <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>State;</hi> They were carried <hi>Captives</hi> from their own Land by <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi> to <hi>Babylon;</hi> The STORY wherof we have at length, II. <hi>Chronicl.</hi> 36. and in the tenth book of <hi>Joſephus</hi> de BEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LO IUDAICO, as alſo in the <hi>Pſ.</hi> 137. there is a hint of it. <hi>By the rivers of Babylon, there wee ſate downe, yea we weept, when wee remembred Zion: Wee hanged our harps upon the willows, in the midſt thereof. For there they that carried us away captive, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us a ſong, &amp; they that wasted us,</hi> required of us <hi>mirth,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Sing us one of the ſongs of Zion: How ſhall wee ſing the LORDS ſong in a ſtrange land? If I forget thee, O IERVSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM, let my right hand forget her cunning. If I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee, let my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth; if I preferre not IERVSALEM above my chiefe joy.</hi> verſ. 1.2.3.4.5.6.</p>
            <p>That even that people whom GOD loves and reſpects,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> may be brought under ſad <hi>bondage,</hi> &amp; that in reference both to their Eccleſiaſtick and Civill ESTATE; This was the lot of the LORDS own peculiar People, the <hi>Iews</hi> were bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they laboured there in <hi>brick</hi> and <hi>mortar,</hi> they wer <hi>Captives</hi> in ASSYRIA, <hi>Captives</hi> in BABYLON, they ar now ſcattered up and down the World, for their <hi>Blasphemy, Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity;</hi> and <hi>Crucifying the LORD of GLORY,</hi> and for not accepting their <hi>MESSIAH</hi> to reigne over them.</p>
            <p>And what hath our <hi>Condition</hi> been theſe ſeverall by gone yeares? Even a <hi>Dark gloomy black Day,</hi> wherein wee had light neither of the <hi>Sun</hi> nor <hi>Moon</hi> nor <hi>Starres</hi> in our civill <hi>Relations.</hi> I do not ſay, That we ar a people beloved of God in ſuch a ſignall way, as the <hi>Iews</hi> wer; They wer a <hi>Royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood:</hi> but I may ſay, That the Lord hath had a ſingular reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to <hi>Britaine,</hi> beyond many Nations, for many ages: And yet becauſe, we were not thankfull to God, for His rich &amp; ſignall <hi>Mercies,</hi> for ſuch a faire day of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> for ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96048:6"/>
long continued <hi>Plenty</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> under ſuch a juſt, equall, ancient and wel-ballanced <hi>GOVERNMENT,</hi> as any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Europe</hi> injoyed, <hi>but like</hi> JESHURUN, <hi>wee waxed fatt in our ſins,</hi> and like a wild untamed <hi>Colt,</hi> did caſt our <hi>Ryder,</hi> &amp; took the reins upon our own lawles necks; Therfore the LORD brought us under a baſe <hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Bondage,</hi> by which our ſins might viſibly be read in our <hi>judgement.</hi> The Lord did juſtly bring us under, by a <hi>Factious, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, Hypocriticall, Treacherous</hi> and <hi>uſurping Party,</hi> who have trode on the necks of three Ancient KINGDOMS, as upon the <hi>Myre</hi> in the ſtreets, and rendered us <hi>Captives</hi> in reference both to our State and Churches <hi>Intereſts.</hi> As for our <hi>State,</hi> IT was clearly and totally over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and razed to the very foundations: our ancient <hi>Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories</hi> changed: <hi>Strangers</hi> impoſed on us for our <hi>Iudges,</hi> men unacquainted with our <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes:</hi> our <hi>Parliaments</hi> with their <hi>power,</hi> totally taken away: <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R GRACIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and <hi>DEAREST KING,</hi> of Sacred and Eternall Memory, <hi>CHARLES the FIRST,</hi> the <hi>PEARLE</hi> of earthly Kings, moſt cruelly, inhumanely and barbarcuſly martyred, and murdered by a <hi>faction</hi> of <hi>Godleſſe, Cruell, Bloudy, Perfidious</hi> and <hi>Hypocriticall TRAYTORS,</hi> and yet under a pretence of <hi>Zeale</hi> for GOD and <hi>juſtice.</hi> O unparalleled helliſh <hi>Villany! <hi>Traytors</hi>
               </hi> who plotted it, <hi>Traytors</hi> who acted it, <hi>traytors</hi> who rejoyced in it, <hi>Traytors</hi> who allowed it, for by that one fatall, O fatall <hi>blow,</hi> theſe <hi>Canniballs</hi> cutted the <hi>throats</hi> of three <hi>KINGDOMS, &amp;</hi> left them bleeding, they did put out the moſt <hi>GLORIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and <hi>SHYNING LIGHT,</hi> that ever ſway'd <hi>Scepter</hi> in <hi>Britaine!</hi> But the <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>bloudy Deſigne,</hi> of that <hi>Murthering Faction,</hi> was not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with that Royall and innocent <hi>Bloud,</hi> after that ſweet <hi>SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LE</hi> was poſted into <hi>GLORY,</hi> to receive the immarceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Crowne,</hi> whether no <hi>Traytor</hi> can reach a <hi>bloudy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96048:6"/>
hand,</hi> then they voted down <hi>MONARCHICALL GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT,</hi> by a <hi>faction,</hi> having ſecluded and forced from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the godly, honeſt and loyall <hi>Party</hi> thereof, they proſcribed, and by an ungodly <hi>Act,</hi> they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherited our moſt <hi>GRACIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S KING</hi> (now reigning by the <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of GOD over their bellies) and laid aſide that <hi>ROYALL FAMILY,</hi> from having any right to the <hi>CROWNE,</hi> and declared Him the Capitall <hi>Enemy</hi> of their new-moulded COMMON-WEALTH, they did raze the <hi>HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> of <hi>LORDS,</hi> that Ancient and wel-ordered <hi>Pillar</hi> of the STATE: And when this Nation of <hi>SCOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> had brought home our Native and Righteous KING, and ſet the <hi>CROWNE</hi> on His Head; Did not that <hi>bloudy faction,</hi> headed by that <hi>Cerberus, <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi>
               </hi> force Him from all His <hi>DOMINIONS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to live as an <hi>Exile</hi> in forreign Nations? Were not our <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> and ancient <hi>Gentry</hi> deſpiſed and abuſed? Were not theſe three KINGDOMS impoveriſh'd with heavy <hi>Aſſeſſes</hi> and ſad <hi>impoſitions,</hi> &amp; the bloud of the <hi>poore</hi> ſucked out, and all to maintayne the <hi>ambition</hi> and <hi>tyrannie</hi> of an uſurping <hi>Faction?</hi> Were not the <hi>Lives</hi> of the moſt godly and moſt faithfull <hi>Subjects</hi> of the three <hi>Nations</hi> made bitter unto them, &amp; their hearts ſadded by being nick-named <hi>Malignants?</hi> And were not the heads of unnaturall factious <hi>Incendiaries</hi> lifted up? Thus was our <hi>State</hi> in perfect <hi>Captivity.</hi> And as for our <hi>Church,</hi> it alſo was in <hi>Captivity.</hi> The juſt <hi>Power, Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of it was trode upon, our Church <hi>Iudicatories</hi> threatned, and not ſuffered to proceed in their own proper affaires, our <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> yea, the <hi>GENERALL ASSEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLY</hi> raiſed by force: and for want of our Native <hi>KING</hi> and lawfull <hi>Magistrats</hi> under Him, to give life and vigour to <hi>Church-ſanctions,</hi> Was not the <hi>Authority</hi> and juſt <hi>ſentences</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> deſpiſed, yea counteracted to, by any who pleaſed? by meanes whereof and of that vaſt and laxe <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> (the great engyne which made theſe men keep the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96048:7"/>
ſadle ſo long) hath not <hi>Poperie</hi> increaſed in the Land? have not all manner of <hi>Heriſies, ſchiſmes,</hi> wild and abominable <hi>opinions</hi> abounded in <hi>Britain?</hi> A whirle-winde of <hi>fancies</hi> &amp; <hi>delusions,</hi> a ſwarme of <hi>Locuſts, <hi>Antiſcripturiſts, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titrinitarians, Arrians, Sabellians, Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Photinians, Pelagians, Socinians, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Enthuſiaſts, Beheminiſts, Antinomians, Levellers, Seekers, Quakers, Ranters, Fift Monarchy men,</hi>
               </hi> a company of proud greedy <hi>Saints.</hi> And beſide all theſe ſad and ſinfull <hi>Captivities</hi> in reference to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> were not mens <hi>Conſciences</hi> in <hi>Captivity</hi> &amp; <hi>Bondage,</hi> being forced with <hi>Oaths,</hi> yea with <hi>Contrary-oaths</hi> and <hi>Tenders,</hi> contrary to former ſolemne <hi>Engagements,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and was not this a perfect <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> That it is no good <hi>Argument</hi> to prove that God hath reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and fully caſten off a <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Nation,</hi> becauſe in his juſt and wiſe Providence, they are brought into ſad <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity;</hi> yee know how often God dealt ſo with theſe <hi>Jewes,</hi> who yet for all that, ſtill remained his People. The externall <hi>Paſſages</hi> of Providence are a very unſure <hi>Rule,</hi> whereby to judge of Gods ſpeciall <hi>Love</hi> &amp; <hi>Favour</hi> to a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> As it is an evill <hi>Argument</hi> to prove that God carries no reſpect to a people, but hath utterly rejected them, and caſten them off, becauſe their <hi>Enemies</hi> prevaile over them, and they are brought under: ſo it is as bad an <hi>Argument</hi> to prove, that God carries a ſingular <hi>Respect</hi> and <hi>Favour</hi> to a people, or alloweth their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings,</hi> becauſe they proſper and are victorious over others; No man, yea no Nation, nor people knowes, whether they be hated or loved of God, by theſe externall paſſages of Providence, <hi>All things fall alyke to all.</hi> But I muſt confeſſe, that this <hi>Turkiſh Argument</hi> built meerly upon externall <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Succeſſe,</hi> hath beene moſt ſinfully &amp; factiouſly made vſe of, in theſe late <hi>Troubles</hi> and <hi>Revolutions.</hi> How many falſe and unjuſt <hi>Concluſions,</hi> have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96048:7"/>
been drawn from the Lords moſt wiſe and providentiall <hi>Actings</hi> in <hi>Britaine</hi> of late, as if God had allowed all theſe horrible <hi>Villanies,</hi> theſe treacherous <hi>Attempts</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> all the <hi>bloud-ſhed, Murders, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, Vſurpations</hi> and <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> which have been acted in the three KINGDOMS, by a factious &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Party,</hi> becauſe they were like ANTIOCHUS, <hi>who practiſed and prospered?</hi> and ſo did theſe in their <hi>miſchiefe;</hi> but God will not take with their <hi>bastards,</hi> although they laid them to the doore of his all wiſe and juſt <hi>Providence,</hi> which ſtands cleare and orient, when <hi>ſhame</hi> now is covering their <hi>faces.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond Point</hi> in the Text, is the JEWS <hi>Deliverance</hi> from their BONDAGE and CAPTIVITY. <hi>(When the LORD brought back the Captivity of Zion:)</hi> Which expreſſion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth two things. 1. The looſing of their <hi>Captivity,</hi> or the taking away the <hi>yoke</hi> of BONDAGE from off their necks. 2. Their <hi>Returning back</hi> to their own LAND in <hi>freedome</hi> and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That although the Lord ſuffer <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> be under <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity,</hi> for a long time, yet Hee can put an end to their <hi>Captivity</hi> when he pleaſes, and he doth ſo when his appointed time comes: for all <hi>times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> are in his hands. The <hi>JEWS</hi> were above 400 yeares <hi>Strangers</hi> and <hi>Bondmen</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but the Lord redeemed them. They were 70 years captive in <hi>Babylon,</hi> but the Lord looſed their <hi>Captivity;</hi> that <hi>Bondage</hi> came to an end, and they returned ſafely to their own land: &amp; thus hath the Lord in his unſpeakable <hi>Mercy,</hi> been pleaſed to deale with <hi>Britain</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland;</hi> the Lord hath reduced our <hi>Captivity.</hi> And as in many things this <hi>Mercy</hi> is great and wonderfull, ſo ſpecially is it in this, that the Lord hath been pleaſed to reduce our <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> ſo ſoone, IT is a <hi>wonder</hi> of the Lords <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that he hath not wreathed the <hi>Yoke</hi> of our <hi>Bondage</hi> about our necks for many generations. His own peculiar people were in <hi>bondage</hi> 70 yeares, in a ſtrange Land: but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96048:8"/>
God hath been pleaſed to ſhorten the years of our <hi>bondage,</hi> and to break the <hi>teeth</hi> of the old and young lions, ſo wee may ſay now, as <hi>Nahum.</hi> cap. 2. verſ. xj. <hi>Where is the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the</hi> Lions, <hi>and the feeding place of the</hi> young Lions? <hi>Where the</hi> Lion, <hi>even the old</hi> Lion <hi>walked, and the</hi> Lions whelp, <hi>and none made them affrayed.</hi> verſ. 12. <hi>The</hi> Lion <hi>did teare in pieces enough for his</hi> whelps, <hi>and ſtrangled for his</hi> Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <hi>and filled his holes with prey, and his dens with ravine.</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>Behold I am againſt thee, ſayeth the LORD of Hoſts, and I will burn her Chariots in the ſmoake, and the ſword ſhall devoure thy</hi> young Lions, <hi>and I will cut off thy</hi> Prey <hi>from the earth, and the voyce of thy Meſſengers ſhall no more bee hard.</hi> Where now is the dwelling of theſe men, who of late did teare theſe <hi>Nations</hi> in pieces, and devoured them like a <hi>Prey?</hi> Are they not gone, &amp; going to their own place.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> That as the Lord can reſtore a baniſhed captive <hi>People</hi> when he pleaſes, ſo he can reſtore an exiled afflicted <hi>KING,</hi> after long and many ſad <hi>Sufferings.</hi> I know not, who can ſufficiently enumerat our <hi>GRACIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S KINGS Sufferings.</hi> Hath he not been a Sufferer ſince his <hi>Child-hood?</hi> What did he ſuffer, before his <hi>DEAREST FATHER'S</hi> unparalleled <hi>Murther?</hi> Conſider how his tender <hi>SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LE</hi> was affected, when theſe ſad <hi>Newes</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me to his eares, of that diſmall <hi>blow</hi> given to his moſt <hi>ILL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STRIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and <hi>LOVING FATHER,</hi> by ſome incarnat <hi>Devils,</hi> whereof one or two were <hi>Masked-Devils.</hi> What hath he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſince? What a miraculous <hi>Eſcape</hi> did the Lord make for him at <hi>Worcester</hi> fight? when an <hi>Hollow Oake</hi> was his <hi>ROYALL PALACE?</hi> What <hi>hazards</hi> hath he been expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to, by <hi>ſea</hi> and <hi>Land?</hi> What <hi>temptations</hi> did hee meete with abroad? What <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Confederacies</hi> have been drawn up againſt him and his juſt <hi>interests,</hi> by forreigne <hi>Princes</hi> &amp; <hi>States?</hi> How unkindly uſed by theſe who ſhould have been friends? How deſerted and forſaken? How toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſo many <hi>billowes</hi> of <hi>Adverſities?</hi> Was he not of late looked upon, but as a broken <hi>veſſell,</hi> in whom the <hi>Enemies</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96048:8"/>
thought there was no <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and but as <hi>water spilt upon the ground?</hi> And yet GOD in his wiſe, juſt and gracious <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> hath been pleaſed to reduce him to his ancient KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOMS, ſafe in <hi>Body,</hi> and ſound in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and hath made his <hi>GLORY</hi> and <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R</hi> more reſplendent and orient, lyke a bright <hi>Sun,</hi> after a dark &amp; tempeſtuous <hi>Night.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is a matter of exceeding great <hi>Praiſe</hi> to GOD, and of wonderfull <hi>Rejoycing</hi> to all the truely <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Loyall,</hi> in the three <hi>KINGDOMS.</hi> But as for <hi>Mal-contents,</hi> let them gnaw their <hi>Tongues</hi> for ſorrow, &amp; feed on their own <hi>Bowels</hi> lyke young <hi>Vipers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>third point</hi> in the Text, is the <hi>JEWS Deliverer.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Who brought back their <hi>captivity?</hi> IT was not <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> it was not their own <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> &amp; <hi>Policy,</hi> nor <hi>Strength,</hi> nor <hi>Power,</hi> but the <hi>LORD JEHOVAH, (When the Lord,)</hi> The LORD had a very immediate and viſible hand in their <hi>deliverance,</hi> as may be read at length in the books of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> And may not <hi>SCOTLAND, ENGLAND</hi> and <hi>IRELAND</hi> ſay, That the <hi>LORD JEHOVAH, hath brought back our Captivity,</hi> Hath not the LORD <hi>made His Arme bare, and His ſteps manifest, and His Hand viſible in our</hi> DELIVERANCE? Who is ſo <hi>blinde</hi> but ſees the very <hi>FIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GER</hi> of GOD, and a wonderfull <hi>PROVIDENCE</hi> in this <hi>Worke,</hi> to be delivered at ſuch a nick of <hi>time,</hi> when few or none were expecting any <hi>deliverance,</hi> but all things loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king worſe and worſe, when that <hi>Fanatique Party</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that pretended <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and had brought all to a meere <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and intended to rule not by the <hi>SPIRIT,</hi> but by the <hi>ſword,</hi> and that none ſhould have <hi>RVLE</hi> or <hi>POWER,</hi> but theſe <hi>Fift Monarchy</hi> men, <hi>Quakers,</hi> &amp; ſuch like deluded giddy <hi>ſpirits?</hi> Yet at that very point of <hi>time,</hi> GOD divided the <hi>Army,</hi> and did ſpirit &amp; animat the honeſt and Loyall <hi>Party</hi> of it, under the Command of that Noble and Valorous <hi>GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALL MONCK,</hi> to ſtand up for lawfull <hi>Authority,</hi> and to call for a free and well-conſtituted <hi>PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT,</hi> which could not be in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> without
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96048:9"/>
a <hi>KING</hi> and houſe of <hi>LORDS.</hi> And although there were many <hi>Plottings</hi> and <hi>Contrivings, Stirrings</hi> and <hi>Riſings,</hi> to hinder the electing and ſitting of a free <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> and many illegall <hi>Qualifications</hi> intended to be put upon <hi>Elections</hi> and perſons elected, yet then did the <hi>LORD</hi> aryſe, and befoole theſe <hi>Firebrands</hi> of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and took them in their own <hi>Snares,</hi> when as they had not ſo much confidence, as to draw a <hi>Sword</hi> in their own defence <hi>(Guiltines within, often makes feeble hands.)</hi> and did not the <hi>LORD</hi> ſend the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of that <hi>Fanatique</hi> party, priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to <hi>LONDON,</hi> the very day before that the <hi>PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT</hi> ſat down, a very <hi>Preſage</hi> from <hi>HEAVEN</hi> of better dayes? and was it not GOD who did put it ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, into the hearts of both houſes of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> of the <hi>ARMY,</hi> and body of the people of the three <hi>KINGDOMES,</hi> of all <hi>Ranks,</hi> to erect <hi>MONARCHIE,</hi> the only <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Lawfull</hi> government of theſe <hi>NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS,</hi> and to ſend for the <hi>KING,</hi> and to bring him home, with great HONOUR and STATE, with the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall <hi>acclamations</hi> of his People? Yea, and all that ſo great a <hi>Worke,</hi> to be brought to paſſe, without one drop of <hi>bloud?</hi> Who ever dreamed of ſuch a peaceable, ſweet and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous REDUCTION of our native KING? and is not this, the very immediat hand of GOD? Yes indeed it is, <hi>(The LORD hath brought back our captivity.)</hi> and to his NAME be the Glory of that <hi>MERCY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> The <hi>Fourth Point</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>(Then wee were lyke them that dreame.)</hi> Now in this <hi>Expreſſion</hi> take notice of two <hi>Things.</hi> 1. That theſe who ar under <hi>Captivity</hi> &amp; <hi>Bondage,</hi> are lyke to men in a <hi>Dream.</hi> 2. When theſe who have been in <hi>Bondage</hi> &amp; <hi>Captivity</hi> are delivered, they ar not at firſt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently awakened out of their <hi>Dream,</hi> that is, they cannot get their <hi>Deliverance</hi> fully beleeved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Theſe who are under <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity,</hi> are lyke theſe in a <hi>Dream,</hi> or Captivity is a <hi>Dream,</hi> or it is as a drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Time,</hi> and that in theſe <hi>Conſiderations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96048:9"/>Theſe that <hi>Dreame,</hi> dreame, in the <hi>Night,</hi> the night is a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> time of <hi>Dreaming,</hi> even ſo is <hi>Captivity</hi> a dreaming <hi>Time,</hi> it is a <hi>Night,</hi> a civill <hi>Night,</hi> it is a time of <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Clouds</hi> upon a Land: And what have theſe late yeares of our <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> been, but a <hi>Night,</hi> a night of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> of <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> a night of <hi>Blackneſſe</hi> &amp; of <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> upon the three <hi>NATIONS,</hi> a night which did <hi>overcloud</hi> all theſe Ancient <hi>lights,</hi> which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhined cleare in <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> a black <hi>night,</hi> which overſhaddowed KING, PARLIAMENT, STATE, CHURCH, NOBILITY, GENTRY, BURROUGHES, MINISTRY and body of the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Captivity</hi> &amp; <hi>Bondage</hi> is like a <hi>dreame</hi> in this reſpect, Theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that dreame are <hi>ſleeping,</hi> ſo a Land under <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> is ſleeping, ordinarly it is ſo. I meane not <hi>ſleeping</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>externall peace</hi> and <hi>reſt, eaſe</hi> and <hi>plenty:</hi> but they are <hi>ſleeping</hi> in a ſenſe <hi>Morall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall:</hi> thus did the IEWS (I beleeve) dreame in their <hi>Captivity,</hi> they were ſleeping in <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſecurity,</hi> under the LORDS <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Anger:</hi> and in this ſenſe, our <hi>bondage</hi> was like a <hi>dream,</hi> for although GOD hath been perſuing theſe Lands theſe ſeverall years bygone, for many <hi>abominations,</hi> and particularly for the cry of <hi>bloud,</hi> and above all, for that Royall and innocent <hi>Bloud</hi> of our Late SOVERAIGN, yet we have ſleeped on in our <hi>ſinnes</hi> and <hi>ſecurity. Wee have keeped fast deceit, and have hid our ſins like</hi> Adam: <hi>wee have been as one that ſleepes on the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe that <hi>ſleepe,</hi> have their <hi>ſenſes</hi> bound up, Their <hi>Eyes</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are ſhute, they <hi>ſee</hi> not, their <hi>Eares</hi> are ſhut, they <hi>heare</hi> not, ſo it fareth ordinatly with a People that are in <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity,</hi> a people lying under <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> Their <hi>Eyes</hi> are ſhut, their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>mindes</hi> are darkned, they do not take to heart their own ſinfull and ſlaviſh <hi>Condition,</hi> they do not ſee nor conſider theſe things which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce for their <hi>reliefe</hi> and <hi>deliverance;</hi> This was the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> people their <hi>Condition</hi> under the <hi>Romanes,</hi> as yee may reade
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96048:10"/>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. (<hi>O if thou hadst knowen, in this thy day, theſe things which belong to thy peace, but now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi> How ſo? They were ſleeping and dreaming in their <hi>ſins.</hi> I am ſure that was our <hi>Condition</hi> during our late <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>bondage,</hi> our <hi>eyes</hi> were ſhute, wee were <hi>dreaming,</hi> we did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee nor conſider rightly, how to win out of our <hi>Thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>ſlavery; Wiſdome, Counſell, Reſolution, Courage</hi> all our politique <hi>Senſes,</hi> for the moſt part at leaſt, were gone! We were become lyke EPHRAIM, <hi>A ſilly doue without an heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>Bondage</hi> is lyke a <hi>Dreame,</hi> becauſe as they who dreame, know not, when they ſhall awake; So a land in <hi>Captivity,</hi> knowes not, when their <hi>Captivity</hi> ſhall be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the <hi>Yoke</hi> broken: In this conſideration alſo, <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were dreaming.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Captivity</hi> is lyke a <hi>Dreame,</hi> becauſe as they who dreame, know not, that they are <hi>Dreaming,</hi> till they awake; ſo a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under <hi>Slavery,</hi> are oftentimes ſo ſtupified &amp; benummed, and do ſit down lyke <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> under the burden, that for the time ſcarce are they ſenſible of their <hi>Condition,</hi> they do not take to heart, that they are in <hi>Bondage,</hi> like <hi>Galley-ſlaves,</hi> who can be merry under their <hi>Guardians</hi> laſh: but when a <hi>Captive</hi> people are reſtored to their wounted <hi>freedome,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> then they finde, that before that, they have been <hi>dreaming,</hi> then they look upon their former baſe diſhonourable, and ſlaviſh <hi>Condition,</hi> with <hi>aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> and <hi>admiration:</hi> thus are theſe three <hi>NATIONS</hi> awakned out of their <hi>dreame:</hi> and theſe who of late were ſtudying to keep the three <hi>KINGDOMS</hi> under <hi>ſlavery</hi> &amp; <hi>bondage,</hi> doth now (I beleeve) finde that they were <hi>drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> alſo, but ſome of them are now awakned out of their <hi>dreame,</hi> when <hi>Iustice</hi> is beginning to perſue them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Theſe that are <hi>dreaming,</hi> their heads are full of <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> and <hi>fancies.</hi> How many thouſand <hi>fancies</hi> float up and down their <hi>Braines?</hi> a <hi>Poor-man</hi> dreames that he is <hi>Rich,</hi> a <hi>Thirſty-man,</hi> that he is <hi>Drinking,</hi> a <hi>Beggar</hi> dreams that he is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96048:10"/>
a <hi>King?</hi> Even ſo a people that is in <hi>Captivity</hi> &amp; <hi>Bondage</hi> are lyke <hi>Dreamers,</hi> ordinarly their heads are full of <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Imaginations:</hi> And I muſt ſay, that never a people were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with more <hi>Fancies, Imaginations</hi> &amp; <hi>Whimſies,</hi> then many in <hi>Britain,</hi> during theſe late <hi>Revolutions</hi> have been. Have not ſome been dreaming to be <hi>Kings?</hi> did not all the <hi>Fift-monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſts</hi> dreame to be <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers</hi> &amp; <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> of the Earth? did they not call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, <hi>The ſword of the Lord &amp; of Gideon?</hi> &amp; that to cut off all the <hi>Canaanits,</hi> in the three <hi>NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS,</hi> &amp; to poſſeſſe All; this was a greedy <hi>Dreame.</hi> Were not ſome dreaming to be <hi>Protectors,</hi> to be <hi>Dictators,</hi> to be the Councell of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitty</hi> of ſafety, yea ſome drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to have this <hi>Place</hi> or that <hi>Place.</hi> Were not <hi>Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Seekers, Levellers,</hi> and all the rable of that fanatique <hi>Party</hi> dreaming ſtrange <hi>dreames?</hi> And did not theſe pretended <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of late, and their Councell of <hi>Estate,</hi> dreame ſtrongly? How many new <hi>fancies</hi> and <hi>modells</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did they hatch in their <hi>brains,</hi> one <hi>Government</hi> this yeare, then another <hi>government</hi> the ſecond yeare, and a third <hi>Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> the third yeare? How often did they change their <hi>Principles</hi> and inſtruments of <hi>Government;</hi> even lyke to young <hi>Children</hi> building <hi>Caſtles</hi> of clay, they build one, that pleaſes not, down goes it, and then another is put up, but in end all is throwne down, and the <hi>Builders</hi> evaniſh &amp; are ſcattered.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Particular</hi> propoſed on this <hi>branch</hi> of the text <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> was this, that when a people, who have been under <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity,</hi> are delivered from their <hi>Bondage,</hi> they are ſo ſurpryſed with their <hi>Deliverance</hi> at firſt, that they can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get it beleeved, they think that it is not reall, but a <hi>dreame,</hi> and ſo was it with the IEWS, at this tyme.</p>
            <p>Becauſe of their long continuance under <hi>Bondage,</hi> they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> were ſo accuſtomed &amp; habituated with <hi>Captivity,</hi> that when they were delivered, they could not get it at firſt beleeved, they thought it a <hi>Dreame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96048:11"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They thought it a <hi>Dreame,</hi> in reſpect of the nick of tyme, when it fell out, that is, when leaſt expected.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They thought their <hi>Deliverance</hi> a dream, and were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſed with it, becauſe of the <hi>Manner</hi> &amp; <hi>Way</hi> how they were <hi>Delivered:</hi> which was without <hi>Armies,</hi> without <hi>Fighting</hi> for their <hi>Delivery</hi> and for their <hi>Liberty,</hi> without <hi>Bloud,</hi> without any common <hi>Conſultation,</hi> or <hi>Meeting</hi> amongſt themſelves, yea without ſo much as petitionating for their own <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They thought it a <hi>Dreame,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of their <hi>Deliverance. Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> to do it, that is, theſe who detained them in <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> They thought it a <hi>Dreame,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Suddenneſſe</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> They thought it a <hi>Dreame,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Repairer</hi> of their breaches. Now let us apply theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> As the JEWS <hi>Condition</hi> was ſad and wofull, and as they were accuſtomed to <hi>Captivity,</hi> and ſo habituated in it, that when they wer indeed <hi>Delivered,</hi> they could not at firſt, get it beleeved, but thought it a <hi>Dreame:</hi> ſo our <hi>Deliverance</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to us at firſt a <hi>Dream,</hi> wee have been ſo ſore toſſed with <hi>Troubles,</hi> ſo accuſtomed to <hi>Slavery,</hi> that when our <hi>Bondage</hi> is broken, by the good hand of our GOD, wee can hardly get it beleeved, wee are lyke men that <hi>Dreame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> As the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of their preſent <hi>Deliverance</hi> was ſtrange, which made it look lyke a <hi>Dreame,</hi> ſo the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINS <hi>Deliverance</hi> was very ſtrange, wee may look upon it as a <hi>Dreame.</hi> And what was it? even the <hi>Pryde</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> of that <hi>Fanatique Party,</hi> who raiſed that pretended <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that they might have wreathed a new <hi>Yoke</hi> upon the necks of the three <hi>KINGDOMS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> As the JEWS <hi>Deliverance</hi> was lyke a <hi>Dreame</hi> to them, in reſpect of the <hi>Time</hi> when GOD did bring it to paſſe, ſo is our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> wrought it at ſuch a <hi>Time,</hi> when wee were not expecting <hi>Deliverance,</hi> but looking for ſadder dayes, when all <hi>Matters</hi> were caſten looſe, all in a <hi>Confuſion,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96048:11"/>
the pretended <hi>Government</hi> in a non-entry, an <hi>Army</hi> on foot to rule by the <hi>Sword,</hi> then and not till then, did the <hi>LORD</hi> ſtep out for out <hi>Help</hi> and <hi>Deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the JEWS <hi>Deliverance</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> looked lyke a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> 
               <hi>Dreame</hi> at firſt, in reſpect of the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of their <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very;</hi> ſo may our <hi>Deliverance</hi> look lyke a <hi>Dreame,</hi> who could have imagined, that an <hi>Engliſh GENERALL,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> ſhould have been the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of <hi>SCOTLANDS Deliverance?</hi> this is lyke a <hi>Dreame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Suddenneſſe</hi> of the JEWS <hi>Deliverance,</hi> made it lyke a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 
               <hi>Dreame,</hi> ſo may wee look on our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> in reſpect of it's <hi>Suddenneſſe.</hi> That noble and worthy <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> having but newly ſit down, when matters are brought to ſuch a paſſe, that our <hi>GRACIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S KING,</hi> is voted unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly <hi>(nemine contradicente)</hi> to have the juſt and undoubted <hi>Right,</hi> to the <hi>CROWNES</hi> of the three <hi>KINGDOMS,</hi> and voted to be ſent for, and ſo brought home in great <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> theſe <hi>Bloudy Parricids</hi> and <hi>Murtherers</hi> of his <hi>DEAREST FATHER</hi> voted <hi>Traytors,</hi> the <hi>KING</hi> ſo much longed for, received and welcomed, by the joyfull <hi>Acclamations</hi> of the three <hi>NATIONS,</hi> and all this in ſo ſhort a <hi>Time:</hi> is not this lyke a <hi>Dreame?</hi> were not people thinking that there would be a long, intricate and doubtfull <hi>Treaty,</hi> between the <hi>KING</hi> and the <hi>PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT?</hi> and were not the <hi>Salamanders</hi> of <hi>Britain</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland</hi> preparing all the <hi>Doubts, Scruples, Obſtructions</hi> &amp; <hi>Remora's</hi> that lay in their power, to caſt in the way, to have rendered ſuch a <hi>Treaty</hi> void and ineffectuall? but the LORD of his rich <hi>Mercy</hi> was pleaſed to preveen, yea and befoole ſuch unthankfull and diſloyall <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> and the KING is at home, before they can get their <hi>ginnes</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and laid.</p>
            <p>As the JEWS <hi>Deliverance</hi> out of <hi>Babylon</hi> looked like a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> 
               <hi>dreame</hi> at firſt, in reſpect of the <hi>Repairer</hi> of their <hi>breaches,</hi> ſo is our <hi>deliverance:</hi> Whom hath GOD made the <hi>Repairer</hi> of our <hi>breaches?</hi> Even our own Native, Gracious KING, by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96048:12"/>
His Gracious <hi>Meſſages</hi> to His <hi>Parliament, Army, Navy,</hi> &amp; to His whole <hi>Subjects</hi> of the three <hi>NATIONS?</hi> Who drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> the <hi>SECOND,</hi> (on whom too many of late looked, <hi>as</hi> upon <hi>water spilt</hi> on <hi>the ground</hi>) that a <hi>PRINCE Exiled,</hi> without <hi>Armies,</hi> without reall and cordiall <hi>Friends</hi> abroad, a <hi>KING</hi> without the <hi>Sinews</hi> of <hi>warre,</hi> ſhould have been the <hi>Repairer</hi> of our <hi>Breaches? This is the LORDS doing, and it is</hi> Marvelous <hi>in Our eyes.</hi> Let all the GLORY of it be His.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The <hi>Last words</hi> are (<hi>Then was Our mouth filled with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> &amp;c.) in theſe <hi>words,</hi> wee have the <hi>Effects,</hi> which the JEWS <hi>Deliverance</hi> wrought on their <hi>Spirits,</hi> it made them to rejoyce exceedingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note>That it is not onely lawfull, but it is alſo the duty of a <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Nation,</hi> whom the LORD hath brought out of <hi>Thraldome</hi> and <hi>Bondage,</hi> and reſtored them to their Ancient and fundamentall <hi>GOVERNMENT,</hi> and <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> and brought home their long wiſhed for, Native KING; to manifeſt the ſenſe of their <hi>Deliverance,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their <hi>hearts</hi> to GOD, but by outward <hi>ſigns</hi> and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que <hi>ſolemnities</hi> of rejoycing before men. When <hi>DAVID</hi> brought up the ARK from <hi>Kiriath Jearim, II. Sam.</hi> 6. Hee did it, with great <hi>state</hi> and <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> and with great out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; publick expreſſions of <hi>joy. DAVID and all the houſe of Iſrael played before the Ark, on all manner of inſtruments, on harps, cornets, cymbals, pſalteries</hi> and <hi>timbrels;</hi> And in the 16 verſ. of that ſame Chapter, DAVID <hi>daunced before the Arke,</hi> and none cenſured him for ſo doing, but a vayne preciſe, hypocriticall ſcold, <hi>Michal. II. Kings</hi> 11. When <hi>Jehoaſh</hi> was crownd, it was done with great <hi>Solemnity</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> So alſo was <hi>SOLOMONS Coronation,</hi> and ſuch was <hi>DAVIDS</hi> returne from beyond <hi>Jordan,</hi> and from the land of the <hi>Hermonits;</hi> All theſe ſignall <hi>Mercies</hi> were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by publick <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> and ſolemnities of <hi>Rejoycings.</hi> This hath been the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of all <hi>Nations, Ages</hi> and <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> upon ſuch eminent occaſions, and wonderfull revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96048:12"/>
of <hi>Mercies.</hi> And who can forbid ſuch Solemne &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Expreſſions of <hi>Joy?</hi> But let it be much locked to, that there be no <hi>Exceſſe,</hi> nor <hi>Ryot,</hi> and no <hi>Offence</hi> be given to GOD, in our publique <hi>Rejoycings.</hi> If I had ſaid two things, I have done.</p>
            <p>If I may compare <hi>Spirituall</hi> things with <hi>Temporalls,</hi> as I <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> truſt there is no <hi>ſin</hi> in it, and the rather, becauſe that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian KINGS,</hi> are <hi>CHRIST'S Vice-gerents</hi> on Earth, I offer to you a paſſage of <hi>Scripture</hi> from <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. <hi>(J Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce greatly, O daughter of</hi> Zion, <hi>ſhout, O daughter of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; <hi>behold, thy KING cometh unto thee: Hee is juſt, &amp; meeke.)</hi> This is indeed a <hi>Propheſie</hi> anent <hi>CHRIST</hi> the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> as it is applyed <hi>Math.</hi> 21 Yet I beleeve it to be no offence, to make ſome <hi>Alluſion</hi> to it; And therefore I ſay, Rejoyce greatly O thou <hi>BRITAIN,</hi> ſhout for joy, for thy <hi>KING</hi> cometh to thee.</p>
            <p>A <hi>KING</hi> cometh, not a <hi>Protector,</hi> not a <hi>Rump-parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".1"/> not a <hi>Fanatique Counſell of State,</hi> not a <hi>Tyrant</hi> but a KING.</p>
            <p>THY KING, not the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> nor of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not the <hi>Turke,</hi> not a <hi>Stranger King,</hi> but THY KING, THY OWN KING, THY NATIVE KING, THY KING by a CIX lineall <hi>Deſcents</hi> from <hi>Royall Blood,</hi> THY KING by <hi>Birth,</hi> THY KING by <hi>Education,</hi> THY KING by <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> THY PROTESTANT KING.</p>
            <p>THY KING cometh <hi>to Thee,</hi> not <hi>Againſt Thee,</hi> THE <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> KING cometh <hi>to us,</hi> not <hi>Againſt us,</hi> with forraigne <hi>Forces,</hi> (which might juſtly have been feared) <hi>venit non irruit:</hi> HEE comes <hi>Softly,</hi> not <hi>Jehu-lyke</hi> marching <hi>Furiouſly,</hi> HEE com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Smoothly</hi> &amp; <hi>Calmly,</hi> lyke the <hi>Waters of Siloah,</hi> not <hi>Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but <hi>Deliberatly,</hi> by the unanimous <hi>Call</hi> of HIS PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, ARMY, NAVY, NOBILITY, GENTRY, city of LONDON, and all the NOBILITY of the THREE NATIONS, by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>HEE comes not to <hi>Oppreſſe,</hi> nor to <hi>Tyranniſe</hi> over His <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Subjects,</hi> but HEE comes <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST,</hi> to reſtore <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96048:13"/>
which was fallen in Our Streets, and where Equity durst not enter, and wher Miſchiefe, was eſtabliſhed by a Law:</hi> HEE comes <hi>I<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST</hi> to erect our Ancient <hi>Iudicatories, Lawes, Iuſt Iudges,</hi> to lift up His afflicted and faithfull <hi>Subjects</hi> Heads, which were trode under, by a faction of <hi>Rebells</hi> &amp; <hi>Uſurpers,</hi> &amp; to bring <hi>Oppreſſors, Tyrants</hi> and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Bloudy men</hi> low.</p>
            <p>HEE comes <hi>MEEK, Iust</hi> &amp; <hi>Meek;</hi> This His <hi>Meekneſſe</hi> is abundantly manifeſted in His MAIESTY'S gracious <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Declarations, Proclamations,</hi> and <hi>Emiſſions,</hi> to HIS PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT, ARMY, NAVY, City of LONDON, to the Houſes of LORDS and COMMONS, and to the whole NOBILITY, GENTRY, MINISTRY, BURROUGHS &amp; people of theſe LANDS. I truſt that GOD hath ſo taught His MAIESTY, and ſo principled HIM for ROYALL GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT, that HE can mixe <hi>Iuſtice</hi> with <hi>Meekneſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Meekneſſe</hi> with <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and hath given to HIM a ſpirit of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> to diſcern between the clamorous pretending <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
               <hi>Whoore,</hi> and the true <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Chyld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (before I cloſe) let mee offer to you, ſome things, by way of advice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Let GOD have the <hi>Praiſe</hi> of this great WORK, of this wonderfull and gracious <hi>Revolution,</hi> for the WORK is His; There hath not a <hi>Revolution</hi> fallen out in our time, not in many <hi>generations</hi> before, wherein the LORDS <hi>Power, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Wiſdome</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> hath been more conſpicuouſly &amp; eminently ſeen, then in this our KINGS <hi>Restauration.</hi> Hath not the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of GOD in a ſudden befooled all theſe <hi>Bloudy-minded, Treacherous, Perfidious, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſloyall <hi>Achitophels</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Macchiavells</hi> in the three KINGDOMS? And therefore let the <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of this WORK, bee to the Holy Name of the LORD our GOD, Who is <hi>Excellent in working, Wonderfull in Counſell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> doing Wonders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next under GOD, Let that Noble, Wiſe, and Religious PARLIAMENT of ENGLAND, That Noble, Wiſe, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96048:13"/>
Valorous GENERALL MONK, now Duke of <hi>Albemar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> Knight of the moſt Noble order of the <hi>Gartar,</hi> &amp;c. Let the honeſt and loyall Party of the <hi>Army,</hi> who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to Him, Let the <hi>Navy,</hi> and all theſe in the three KINGDOMS, both of the NOBILITY, GENTRY, BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RONS, MINISTERS, BURROUGHS, &amp; all who had an hand in this great WORK (which ſome have been ſtudying like <hi>Foxes</hi> in their den's and <hi>Conyes</hi> in their holes, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminde) I ſay, Let all theſe who have been inſtrumentall to carry on this great WORK and REVOLUTION, have their own deſerved <hi>Estimation</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and let them be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on with <hi>Love, Respect</hi> &amp; <hi>Honour</hi> as Lovers of <hi>Religion,</hi> of their Native KING, and their Countreyes <hi>Honour, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe, as poliſhed ſhafts in the LORDS right Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you, let the KING have the benefit of your <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Prayers,</hi> that is one of the beſt <hi>Offices,</hi> that yee can do to HIM, <hi>Pray</hi> for HIM often, not for a <hi>Forme,</hi> but in good <hi>Earneſt,</hi> and from a pious Loyall <hi>Affection,</hi> hold up HIS <hi>Condition</hi> to GOD, when ye remember your own; Pray the LORD, <hi>to eſtabliſh HIS THRONE in Righteouſnes,</hi> to make the <hi>CROWNE</hi> to flowriſh on HIS HEAD, &amp; the HEADS of HIS POSTERITY, while <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> indure. Pray that no <hi>Treaſon,</hi> nor <hi>Traytor</hi> at any tyme may reach the <hi>CROWNE,</hi> that GOD would bleſſe His MAIES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY, with a wiſe, Godly, faithfull, and Loyall <hi>Counſell,</hi> with an holy, obedient, and peaceable <hi>Clergy,</hi> with a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive, contented, Loyall <hi>People,</hi> that HEE may be a <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke</hi> for <hi>Truth, Godlineſſe, Religion, Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> that HEE may be a <hi>Nurſing Father</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancer</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and that HEE may <hi>Scatter the wicked of the land, with his eyes,</hi> and that HEE may be a <hi>Diademe,</hi> in the hand of the LORD of HOSTS, and a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne</hi> for all the <hi>Kings</hi> of the world to imitate: For there was never KING of <hi>Britaine,</hi> that had more need of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Prudence</hi> &amp; <hi>Forſight,</hi> then HIS MAIESTY who now
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96048:14"/>
Reignes. Never any of His <hi>Royall Anceſtors</hi> did come to their <hi>Crowne</hi> in a more difficult tyme, Never a KING had greater variety and tempers of <hi>Spirit,</hi> to deale with, nor more difficulty to give juſt and reaſonable ſatisfaction and content to ſo many ſeverall and contrary <hi>Interests.</hi> Never any of His <hi>Royall Predeceſſors</hi> had more <hi>Enemies,</hi> ſome known, and ſome vailed, who can very ſliely and ſubtilly drop out words, for His <hi>Diſadvantage,</hi> ſo the KING ſtands much in need of the <hi>Prayers</hi> of His Godly and loyall <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> wherfore let our hearty <hi>Prayers</hi> be to GOD for HIM.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Beware to give care to any ſiniſtrous <hi>Reports, Suggeſtions</hi> or <hi>Miſinformations</hi> againſt the KING'S <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> There is and was a generation in <hi>BRITAINE,</hi> who made it their trade and game <hi>(Religiouſly &amp; Devotly enough)</hi> to blaſt His MAIESTY'S FATHERS <hi>Reputation,</hi> whoſe <hi>Memory</hi> is now ſacred, &amp; will be as a ſweet favour to ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Generations,</hi> when the <hi>Memory</hi> of theſe vile <hi>Aſperſers</hi> ſhall rote and ſtink in the <hi>Dust<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Yea that ſame evill <hi>Spirit,</hi> is not yet baniſhed away, ſtudying what lyes in its power in a flie, ſubtile, hypocriticall, clandeſtine <hi>Way,</hi> under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> to ſuggeſt <hi>Prejudices</hi> in the mynd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſimple and well-minded <hi>People,</hi> whom they have abuſed too long againſt the <hi>KING<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> whereas HEE hath given farre more evident <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> in the midſt of many ſtrange <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations</hi> to the <hi>Truth</hi> of the Proteſtant <hi>Religion,</hi> then any or all of theſe diſloyall <hi>Whiſperers.</hi> Beware to heare ſuch falſe <hi>Inſinuations,</hi> for they ſmell worſe then <hi>Hemlock in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Field.</hi> I do not ſpeake this, with any reference to this <hi>Place</hi> in particular. I know &amp; that upon good <hi>Grounds</hi> from many years <hi>Experience,</hi> that <hi>ABERDENE</hi> might of old, and yet may (be it ſpoken without <hi>Envy</hi> or <hi>Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) compare for <hi>Loyalty</hi> to their <hi>KING,</hi> with any City in <hi>BRITAINE,</hi> but I ſpeake this as a generall <hi>Warning,</hi> for the whole land, for ther hath been much <hi>Sin</hi> that way in <hi>BRITAINE;</hi> and if any now ſhould follow ſuch diſloyall <hi>Steps,</hi> they ought to be marked and diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96048:14"/>Beware to have an hand, or any way to be acceſſory, to any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> thing, which directly or indirectly may tend to, or look like a <hi>Prejudice</hi> to <hi>MONARCHICALL GOVERNMENT,</hi> or to the ſhaking one <hi>Pinne</hi> of it looſe. It was moſt wyſly ſaid by our late <hi>Martyr KING</hi> of bleſſed <hi>Memory,</hi> that the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> then was like to a <hi>Watch,</hi> when it is taken down, if one <hi>Pinne</hi> be ſet wrong, it will marre all, and make all go <hi>Wrong.</hi> Wee have found <hi>HIM</hi> a true <hi>Prophet</hi> in that, as in many other things. Now therefore ſince GOD in His deepe <hi>Wiſdome</hi> and wonderfull <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> hath reduced Our <hi>NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVE KING</hi> and ſet up <hi>MONARCHY,</hi> the Ancient and Lawfull <hi>Government</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> let all the <hi>Subjects</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the leaſt occaſion, directly or indirectly to looſe the ſmalleſt <hi>Pinne</hi> of it. Let all the <hi>Subjects</hi> know that it's their <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> to live under their <hi>NATIVE KING,</hi> under their Ancient, fundamentall <hi>Government</hi> and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>Lawes,</hi> and not under the ſword of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> &amp; <hi>Tyrants.</hi> Have wee not ſore ſmarted already under the change of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</hi> Have wee not found a fancyed Comonwealths <hi>Finger</hi> heavier then Our former Lawfull <hi>KINGS Loynt?</hi> Let us account <hi>Government</hi> a precious tender <hi>Thing, Let us not midle with them that are given to Change.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly be content to beare <hi>Burthens</hi> for a time, to pay publique <hi>Aſſeſſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> which yet the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of affairs call for. What was payed to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> let non grudge to pay to Our juſt <hi>KING,</hi> for the great <hi>Affaires</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> And I am confident that a ſhort time ſhall eaſe theſe <hi>Nations</hi> of that, which for the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is not rationally poſſible to be eaſed of: but I need not to ſpend tyme on <hi>Exhortations</hi> of this nature, as to <hi>Loyalty</hi> &amp; <hi>Cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> under <hi>burthens</hi> to this <hi>Honorable</hi> &amp; <hi>Loyall</hi> City; in whoſe eſtimation &amp; hearts the KINGS <hi>Majeſty</hi> is moſt deare and precious. <hi>Love makes you Loyall.</hi> I ſay no more, but <hi>Feare</hi> GOD &amp; <hi>Honour the</hi> KING. GOD <hi>bleſſe</hi> K. CHARLES II. KING <hi>of great</hi> BRITAINE &amp;c. Now to him who is KING of kings, &amp; LORD of Lords, be <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
